Guide to the Laura Bailey Collection of Gender and Transgender Materials
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Laura Bailey collection of gender and transgender materials
1850-2013
GEN MSS 787
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
74.43
(87 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
The Laura Bailey Collection of Gender and Transgender Materials consists of a broad range of visual materials, including photographs, postcards, and many types of printed ephemera; manuscript materials, and audiovisual materials. The collection is organized largely as it was received from Bailey, with many materials in binders according to category of gender or transgender culture or performance as assigned by Bailey. Also included is a catalog for the collection compiled by Bailey and the hand-written index cards she used to catalog it.
Bailey, Laura E., 1951-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Laura Bailey on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2010. The index cards were the gift of Laura Bailey, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 24 (audiovisual materials): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 88 (compact disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Laura Bailey
As a natural born lifetime collector of the ephemeral, Laura Bailey has bought and sold, as both a collector and a rare book and rare paper collectibles dealer professionally in the international markets. In addition to real life experience, Laura's academic credentials include New York University and The New School for Social Research.
Her life experiences included touring in a band as a multitalented musician - (trumpet, organ, all keyboard instruments, and electronic music),- working in the hospitality industry as both manager and owner of a resort hotel in Eastern Long Island, and owning a bookstore in New York City's historic Greenwich Village. Laura Bailey was a conscientious activist even before Stonewall in 1969, and remains a staunch supporter of Human Rights today.
Laura's expansive varied collections have included beat poetry, original 20th Century art, Mayan art, stamps, and erotica. Laura continues her passions for collecting materials reflective of cultural diversity, societal taboos, and those discriminated against, ignored, persecuted and forgotten. Laura's current collection in inventory and sheer numbers ranges in the hundreds of thousands.
Scope and Contents
The Laura Bailey Collection of Gender and Transgender Materials consists of a broad range of visual materials, including photographs, postcards, and many types of printed ephemera; manuscript materials, and audiovisual materials. The collection is organized largely as it was received from Bailey, with many materials in binders according to category of gender or transgender culture or performance as assigned by Bailey. Also included is a catalog for the collection compiled by Bailey and the hand-written index cards she used to catalog it.
The collection has been cataloged in two groups. The printed component, comprised of books, magazines, newsletters, and a variety of printed ephemera, is in the process of being cataloged in the Yale Library's online catalog. The archival component is described in brief in this finding aid. More detailed descriptions will be added in the future. The collection catalog and index cards detail the contents of the entire collection, including the printed component.
The first piece Laura Bailey bought in the 1960's was a digest entitled "Muscle Man in Silks" about a body builder who "had a weakness for women's silk lingerie." She went on to gather, widely and internationally, any material that exhibited or commented on gender variation: photographs, postcards, flyers and programs for night clubs, sheet music, and clippings. These cover a wide range of gender expression, from drag queens and kings to cowgirls and bearded ladies. This finding aids lists materials as received from Laura Bailey – most of them gathered into thematic groups in scrapbooks and photo albums.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series: Series I. Photographs; Series II. Manuscript and Printed Materials; Series III. Correspondence; Series IV. Index Cards; and Series V. Audiovisual Materials.
Gender expression; Gender identity; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Photographs; Bailey, Laura E., 1951-
- Photographs, 1850s-1990s; Series I; 17.19; (17 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Materials are stored in binders as received from Laura Bailey, which are arranged in rough alphabetical order by the title assigned to the binder by Bailey.
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists of photographic material, with associated printed material, organized into categories of gender and transgender culture or performance as assigned by Laura Bailey.
  - "11 photos", circa 1940 (Box 1)
  - Bernhardt, Sarah (Box 1)
  - Bearded Ladies (Box 1)
  - Carrousel de Paris, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Le Carrousel de Paris on Tour, Florence, Italy - Photo by Locche, circa 1960 (Box 25 Oversize)
  - Le Carrousel, "Final Act" - Photo by Karuna, 1959 (Box 25 Oversize)
  - Le Carrousel on Tour, Belgium (?), circa 1960 (Box 25 Oversize)
  - Le Carrousel on Tour, Florence, Italy, 1960 (Box 25 Oversize)
  - Cartes de visite of American Burlesque Actresses / Performers / Singers, 1870s (Box 1)
    Contains a group of twenty Carte de visite photographs.
  - Caution - explicit photographs (Box 1)
  - Coccinelle, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Coccinelle et CriCri Mory, Limoger, 1959 (Box 25 Oversize)
  - Cowgirls (Box 1)
  - Cross Dressers (Box 2)
  - Crossdressed Cabinet Cards, 1880s (Box 2)
  - Crossdressed Cabinet Cards - Theatricals, 1880s-1890s (Box 2)
  - Crossdressing Amateurs (Box 26 Oversize)
  - Crossdressing Comedy (Box 2)
  - Crossdressing Mounted Photographs, 1850s-1910s (Box 2)
  - Eltinge, Julian, 1904-1917 (Box 2)
  - Explicit photographs (Box 2)
  - Explicit photographs (Box 2)
  - Female Impersonators, 3 (Box 3)
  - Female Impersonators (Box 27 Oversize)
  - Female Impersonators (Box 28 Oversize)
    Contains some printed material.
  - Female Impersonators, 1880s-1930s (Box 3)
  - Female Impersonators, 1930s-1950s (Box 3)
  - Female Impersonators, Amateur, 1943-1960s (Box 3)
  - Female Transformists (Box 3)
  - Gerbiou, Francois, 1960s-1970s (Box 3)
  - Halloween in S.F. (Box 3)
  - K.C. Show, Memorial Hall, Melrose, November 24/[19]30, framed. (Box 32 Oversize)
  - Klaw, Irving - Female Impersonators (Box 4)
  - A Lady at Home (Box 4)
  - "La Loge de Thalie", 1990s (Box 4)
  - "Les Girls" (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 5)
  - Miss Gay Black Ohio
    - Miss Gay Black Ohio, 1995 etc., 1993-1997 (Box 5)
    - Miss Black Gay Ohio, Miss Groovy Guy, etc. (Flower Binder), 1960s; 1982-1983 (Box 5)
      Contains personal pictures from the 1960s, including school photographs.
    - Mr. Groovy Guy, 1992 (Box 5)
    - Miss Black Gay Ohio, 1977-1980; 1982; 2 (Box 6)
    - Miss Black Gay Ohio, 1985 - Miss Groovy Guy, 1988, 1985, 1988 (Box 6)
  - Parisian Criminals, 1980s (Box 6)
  - Photographs, 1890s-1960s (Box 6)
  - "Photos", 1980s (Box 28 Oversize)
  - Portraits, 1990s (Box 29 Oversize)
  - Portraits, 1990s (Box 30 Oversize)
  - P.O.W. (Box 7)
  - P.O.W. (Box 7)
  - Sicilian boy posed in woman's clothing, photographs by Baron Wilhelm von Gloeden., circa 1898 (Box 7)
  - Stereo Cards, 1880s (Box 7)
  - Studio Sinclair
    - Bambi - Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Biche - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Capucine - Photo Charles Sinclair, 3 (Box 31 Oversize)
    - D'Olban, Alexandra - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Daury, Laurence - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Dollar, Julia - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Dolly - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Esperanza - Studio Sinclair, 2 (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Giovanna - Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Irene - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Jessy - Studio Sinclair, 2 (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Lee, Olga - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Mitsou - Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Mory, CriCri - Sinclair, circa 1960 (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Nathalie - Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Paule, Frederique - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Photo Charles Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Suzannah - Studio Sinclair (Box 31 Oversize)
    - Untitled portrait (Box 31 Oversize)
  - Transvesties - Photos & Negs (Box 7)
  - Transvestism (Box 7)
  - Transvestism & Crossdressing Theater, 1893 (Box 7)
  - Transvestite Fantasies (Box 8)
  - Wallace, Carroll (Box 8)
  - Women in Uniform (Box 8)
  - Women Smoking (Box 8)
  - XXX - Explicit Photographs (Box 8)
  - XXX - Explicit Photographs (Box 9)
  - Zurich, Fans of the Carrousel Show, 1961 (Box 33 Oversize)
- Manuscript and Printed Materials, 1890s-2008; Series II; 26.42; (23 boxes)
  This series consists of various manuscript and printed materials including clippings, newspapers and magazines, and published pictures, organized into categories of gender and transgender culture or performance as assigned by Laura Bailey. Also includes the collection catalog created by Laura Bailey. Some photographic material is also present.
  - Advertising Clippings, 1977; 2009 (Box 33 Oversize)
  - Artists/Art Clippings - Transgender Artists, Photographers, 1980s-2000s (Box 34 Oversize)
  - Amateur Crossdressing - postcards, 4 (Box 10)
    Contains some photographs.
  - Big Mama (Box 10)
  - Book Reviews, 2000s (Box 34 Oversize)
  - Burmel Publishing from Early 60s Digest, 1960s (Box 34 Oversize)
  - Carmella, Diane De Lys, and Julie Gibson (Box 11)
  - Clippings, 1970s - 2000s (Box 11)
  - Clippings, 1988-2007; 2 (Box 35 Oversize)
    Contains copies of The Village Voice and New York Newsday.
  - Clippings, 1980s-2000s (Box 36 Oversize)
    Contains The Villager and New York Newsday.
  - Clippings, 1990s-2000s (Box 36 Oversize)
  - Clippings, 2000s (Box 36 Oversize)
  - Clippings, 1990s-2000s (Box 36 Oversize)
  - Clippings, 1990s-2000s; 3 (Box 37 Oversize)
  - Clippings - entertainment, 2000s (Box 38 Oversize)
  - Clippings - miscellanous, 1987; 2007 (Box 38 Oversize)
  - Clippings - movie reviews, 1982-2004 (Box 38 Oversize)
  - Clippings - Transgender Movies/TV Reviews, Articles, etc., circa 1994 (Box 38 Oversize)
  - Coccinelle, 1960s-1970s (Box 18)
    Includes photographs and periodicals.
  - Coccinelle Movies, list (Box 11)
  - Comedy (Box 11)
  - Curtis, Jackie - Files, 1985-2004 (Box 39 Oversize)
  - D'Arc, Jeanne (Box 11)
  - Darling, Candy - Files, 2006-2009 (Box 39 Oversize)
  - Eltinge, Julian - posters and flyers (Box 39 Oversize)
  - Eltinge, Julian - postcards (Box 11)
  - Emancipation (Box 11)
  - Entertainers/Singers, 1990s-2000s (Box 40 Oversize)
  - Female impersonation (Box 41 Oversize)
  - Female Impersonators - postcards (Box 11)
  - Female Impersonators - postcards, 4 (Box 12)
    Includes some photographs.
  - Female Impersonators - postcards, 2 (Box 13)
  - Female Transformists - postcards, 2 (Box 13)
  - Female Transformists - postcards (Box 14)
  - Gay & Transvestite Ephemera, 1980s-2000s (Box 14)
  - General Transgender News, 1980s-2000s (Box 42 Oversize)
  - Jorgensen, Christine - clippings, 1970s-2000s (Box 42 Oversize)
  - Julian Eltinge in the Crinoline Girl (Box 14)
  - La S.D.N. et le Désarmement. Pen and ink by Fernand Couderc. Framing by H. Montchanin, 6. Rue Ferdinand-Gambon, NEVERS, 1927 (Box 42 Oversize)
  - Lawsuits/Transg. Bias, Crime against Transgendered, 2000s (Box 42 Oversize)
  - Lingerie or Clothing, 1970s-2000s (Box 43 Oversize)
  - Manuscript (?) (Box 14)
  - Michou pin (Box 14)
  - Obits, 1990s-2000s (Box 43 Oversize)
  - Original Art (Box 14)
  - Pageants, advertisements, other events - binder, 1990s (Box 14)
  - Pageants and other events, 1990s (Box 14)
  - Pageants and other events, 1990s (Box 18)
  - Part-Time Ladies - postcards (Box 15)
  - Pictorial Supplement (Section M) (Box 15)
  - P.O.W. (Box 15)
  - Serials - postcards (Box 15)
  - Serials - postcards, 2 (Box 16)
  - Sports, 2000s (Box 43 Oversize)
  - Theatre, 1990s-2000s (Box 44 Oversize)
  - Transgender Crime, Criminals (Box 44 Oversize)
  - Transgender History, clippings, 1990s-2000s (Box 45 Oversize)
  - Transgender Periodicals, Clippings, also Books; Star Distributions Catalog; LGBT Center Flyers & Related, 2007-2008 (Box 45 Oversize)
  - Transvestism, Transexuals - Film, Sheet Music, and other Ephemera, 1890s-1920s (Box 46 Oversize)
    Includes photographs.
  - Transvestite Bibliography (Box 18)
  - Women in Uniform (Box 16)
  - Wood, Ed - Clippings, circa 1994 (Box 45 Oversize)
  - WWII P.O.W. (Box 17)
  - Laura Bailey Collection Catalog
    Collection catalog created by Laura Bailey.
    Catalog is arranged alphabetically by section.
    - Addendum to Catalog (Box 47)
    - The Laura Bailey Transgender Collection (Box 47)
    - Laura Bailey Transgender Collection Pictorial Supplement (Box 47)
    - Transgender Digests (Box 47)
    - Transgender Magazines (Box 47)
    - Transgender Studies (Box 47)
- Correspondence, 2005-2007; Series III; 0.25; (1 box)
  Material is arranged in rough alphabetical order.
  The series consists of correspondence related to gender and transgender collected by Laura Bailey.
  - Guillard, A.- correspondence, 2005-2006; 2 (Box 19)
  - Guillard, A. - Crossdresser's Correspondence - Sevres, France, 2005 (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence and articles, 2006-2007 (Box 19)
- Index Cards, Series IV; 2.63; (4 boxes)
  The series consists of manuscript index cards used by Laura Bailey to catalog the collection. The index cards catalog both the manuscript and visual materials in this archival collection and the printed component cataloged separately. The cards are housed in their original boxes.
  - Bearded Ladies / Photograph / Studies / Movie Record. (Box 20)
  - Clippings, Photos (Box 20)
  - Erotica – Spanking, loose index cards (Box 20)
  - Postcards - Crossdressing - Xeroxed (Box 20)
  - Transgender Cards, loose index cards (Box 20)
  - Transgender / Crossdressing (Box 20)
  - Transgender / Crossdressing (Box 21)
  - Transgender / Crossdressing Magazines A-Z Box 1 (Box 21)
  - Transgender / Crossdressing Magazines A-Z Box 2 (Box 21)
  - Transgender Digests and Fetish Digests (Box 21)
  - Transgender Postcards (Box 22)
  - TV Paperbacks A-Z Box 1 (Box 22)
  - TV Paperbacks A-Z Box 2 (Box 23)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1951-1980s; Series V; 0.25; (1 box)
  Audiovisual materials are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
  The series consists of film and phonographic records.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - Cocinelle 45 RPM Records (Box 24)
  - Cocinelle - striptease, 8mm color film (Box 24)
  - Curtis, Jackie, 1951; 1983 (Box 24)
    Includes The Human Voice by Jean Cocteau (1951), and two 45 RPM records.
  - Michou 45 RPM records, all signed/inscribed (Box 24)
- July 2013 Acquisition, circa 1917-2010s
  Organized into four groupings: Index Cards; Photographs and Artwork; Printed Materials; Restricted Fragile.
  - Index cards, circa 1990s-2000s (Box 48)
  - Photographs and artwork
    - Prisoner of war photographs and related journal, circa 1917 (Box 49)
    - Photographs and postcards (Box 50)
    - Photographs and artwork, 1920s-2000s (Box 51 (Oversize))
  - Printed materials
    - Magazines
      - The Advocate, 1990s-2000s (Box 52)
      - The Advocate, 1990s-2010s (Box 53)
      - The Advocate, 2010s (Box 54)
      - Egg, 1990 (Box 55)
      - Go! / Go NYC; Get Out Weekly, 1990s-2000s (Box 56)
      - HX., 2000s-2010s (Box 57)
      - HX., 2000s (Box 58)
      - Leg Show, 1990s-2000s (Box 59)
      - Next, 1990s-2010s (Box 60)
      - Next, 1990s-2010s (Box 61)
      - Out / Out Travel., 1990s-2000s (Box 62)
      - Out / Out Travel., 1990s-2000s (Box 63)
      - Out / Out Travel., 1990s-2000s (Box 64)
      - Penthouse / Penthouse Letters., 1970s-1980s (Box 65)
      - Playboy, 1960s-2000s (Box 66)
      - Playboy, 1960s-2000s (Box 67)
      - Playboy, 1980s-2000s (Box 68)
      - Assorted magazines: Equality; Vice; New York; Rolling Stone; New Yorker; Vanity Fair; Genre; NYC Pride Guide; Project X., 1990s-2000s (Box 69)
      - Assorted magazines: Hustler; Oui; Chic; Adult Film World Guide; Puritan., 1970s-2000s (Box 70)
      - Assorted magazines: Eros; Select; Club., 1970s-2000s (Box 71)
      - Assorted magazines: Viva; Adult Video News; Club International; Gallery, 1970s-1980s (Box 72)
      - Assorted magazines: The Gay and Lesbian Review; Genesis; Live!; Video Review; Gallery & Studio; Time Out New York; SoHo Journal; Dial Thirteen; High Society; Details; Metrosource; Male; Dapper; Velvet; Gentleman's Companion; Roomates; High Society's Celebrity Skin; Partner; Lucky 7; Theatre Arts; Elite; Cavalier; Expose!; Adam; Cheri; Hustler Kinky Sex; l'Agenda de Tetu; Cinefantastique; The L Magazine; Pride; Paper; Pulse; The Guide., 1970s-2010s (Box 73)
    - Ephemera and other printed materials
      - Collection notes, ephemera, catalogs, travel material, LGBT resources, Candy Darling clippings, 1949-2010s (Box 74)
      - Posters, calendar, 1970s -2000s (Box 75 (Oversize))
      - Posters, 1970s-1980s (Box 76 (Broadside))
    - Annotated clippings
      - Adam Film World, Adult Video News, Advocate, AM New York, 1980s-2010s (Box 77)
      - Daily News, 1980s-2010s (Box 78)
      - Downtown Express, East Villager & Villager, East Villager, Gay City, Gay City News, Independent Film, Interview magazine, LA Times, The L Magazine, Metro, miscellaneous clippings, 1980s-2010s (Box 79)
      - Miscellaneous clippings, 1980s-2010s (Box 80)
      - Mojo, Museum of Modern Art, Newsday, New York Blade, New York Press, Next, The Onion, Out, Playboy Magazine, Rolling Stone, The Slammer, Time Out, Time Out NY, Variety, Whisper Magazine, WWD, 1980s-2010s (Box 81)
      - New York Post, 1980s-2010s (Box 82)
      - Village Voice, 1980s-2010s (Box 83)
      - Village Voice, 1980s-2010s (Box 84)
      - New York Times, 1980s-2010s (Box 85)
      - New York Times, 1980s-2010s (Box 86)
      - New York Times, miscellaneous clippings, 1980s-2010s (Box 87)
  - Restricted fragile
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Electronic media, (3 CDs) (Box 88)